Eye movement detected.
What is two plus two?
Incorrect.
Cognition assessment
What is two plus two?
Incorrect.
You have been
in an induced coma.
You may experience some
memory loss difficulty speaking.
Body movement detected.
For your own safety, please
return to the medical platform.
Where am I?
Please remember muscle function
has not yet been restored.
People!
Hello?
Where am I?
Red leather, yellow leather.
Why is there an atomic resolution
scanning electron microscope?
Why do I know that?
Am I smart?
Hello?
- Please record video diary.
- No.
Can I speak to the
person in charge?
- The, uh, captain.
- Captain Yáo, Li-Jie.
Deceased.
Yeah, where, um,
are the living people?
Dr. Ryland Grace.
End of manifest.
I can't be the only
person here. Right?
Pilot detected.
No! No. No-No. Not the pilot.
Uh call, uh, Houston.
Unknown command.
Operation Go Home...
- in effect.
- Invalid operation.
That's the sun! There it is.
So, what are we,
like, Neptune-ish?
Let's crank up the
radio and call Earth.
Current transmission time to Earth is 11
years, 10 months, 14 days and 6 hours.
No. Nope.
You're wrong.
I need a map.
Oh.
Uh
That's so far.
That's not our sun.
Where is the fuel?
Wait.
We are just minutes
away from the fly-by
through the Petrova
line near Venus.
So, what can you tell us
about the ArcLight probe?
What do we expect to find?
The image we see will be coming
from the onboard microscope.
Oh! Oh my God.
Sorry. I have to go now.
♪ Sound waves are physical. ♪
♪ And at different frequencies, ♪
♪ they make different pattern-- ♪
♪ No, pattern-- ♪
♪ They make different patt-- ♪
Olivia, can you help
me out? There we go!
Whoa!
Yeah.
Are they really eating the sun?
The space dots?
That is a great
question, uh, Rekha.
And I'd be curious what
your parents think about that.
I'm not sure it
should come from me.
Hey! Who wants to play a game of
the bean bag is lava!
Lava! Lava! Lava!
What is the speed
of light, Olivia?
Uh
It's melting your hands, Olivia!
186,000 miles per second!
Oh! Give her a
round of applause.
That is awesome.
What is the Petrova line?
Pass!
You can't pass!
I just did.
Lava! Lava! Lava!
Come on, guys.
Two years ago...
a radio telescope enthusiast
named Irina Petrova,...
she noticed that there
was a streak of infrared light
from the sun to Venus.
And that is now known
as the Petrova line.
- That's it.
- That's the dots?
- They think so.
- What dots?
These dots.
They sent a probe
up to the Petrova line,
and this is what they found.
Are they eating the sun?
They seem to be...
dimming the sun a tiny,
teeny-weeny, little bit.
So, no big whoop.
It's a small whoop.
It's a small-to-medium whoop.
Over the next 30
years, the Earth could...
cool maybe 10 to...
15 degrees.
So it is a big whoop.
I heard that all
the crops will die,
the economy will free-fall,
and half the Earth
will die of starvation.
- Well.
- We're all gonna die!
Yeah, it's true.
You're forgetting something.
Guys, guys! That's if that
were to happen. Right?
They're gonna figure this out.
Right now, the best minds
in the entire world are on it.
Good morning, Dr. Grace.
I'm up!
Knock, knock.
Who's there?
Not good at jokes.
Not good at jokes who?
Dr. Grace?
Maybe.
Eva Stratt. I'm with
the Petrova Task Force.
I need your help.
- Me.
- Did you write this?
Oh.
I'm interested in
this section here.
- Uh
- Page 31.
"The Goldilocks Zone Is For Idiots:
Why Everyone Is Wrong About Life."
That was a long time ago.
Do you stand by what you wrote?
I was fired for standing
by what I wrote.
You were fired for calling the
leading scholar in your field
"a staggering waste of carbon" at the
UNESCO conference in Denmark.
You heard about that, huh?
Look, I don't know what this is,
but, uh, I think I'm not s--
That's lava.
- It's not.
- Okay.
No one in your field
wants anything to do
with you because you
refused to back down
from a very unpopular
view, and I can
give you a chance to
prove them all wrong.
- Uh Kevin, no running.
- I'm not.
Well, joke's on them
because I don't even care. So
I think you do care.
You're just running away
because you're scared.
No, I'm not.
Do you still believe water is
unnecessary for life to evolve?
Uh
Look, there is nothing magical
about hydrogen and oxygen.
Water is required
for life on Earth, sure.
But a completely
different planet
might have completely
different conditions.
I don't know why that
makes me such a nut.
I need you to come with us.
- Sorry, I didn't catch your name.
- Carl.
- Carl. Hi.
- Dr. Grace,
Petrova line samples
splashed down last night.
I want you to tell me what
they are, how they work.
I am a teacher at
Grover Cleveland Middle.
And you have a doctorate
in molecular biology.
And I ride a bike to work,
and it's not for exercise.
So I'm sure there
are thousands of other
- people who are better--
- It survives on
the surface of the sun.
Does that sound like a
water-based lifeform to you?
The sun's really
dying, isn't it?
Yeah.
Is all of this necessary?
Yes.
Please analyze
the Petrova sample.
Um
Just one thing. The entire
room is filled with argon.
Just try not to rip your suit.
Uh
Am I expendable? Is
that why you want me?
That's not the only reason.
It's almost like you
don't care if I die.
Hold on. You have
to talk about it?
The consensus here is that it
would be preferable if you did not die.
Thanks, guys.
Oh.
Welcome to Earth.
Are they alive?
They're moving.
So they're alive.
Yes, they're moving, but that
could be for many reasons.
What are they made of?
It's gonna take a long
ti-- It took like...
200 years to figure out how
bacteria works, so...
Please do it faster.
I'm just going through the
whole light spectrum here.
Wow!
You're not gonna believe this.
Nothing happened.
I can't see into these buggers.
Amazing.
X-rays, microwaves,
gamma rays, visible light.
Nothing!
Ooh, ooh, ooh, I've been
dying to do this all day!
It's a cell!
It's a cell. Wake
up! It's a cell!
It's a tiny alien
cell. You guys!
Applause.
Guys! This is first contact!
With life outside of the--!
Uh-oh.
Oh, it died.
What?
This is great news.
Now we can find out
what they're made of.
You guys fired up?
Yes!
Right?
Carbon.
Oxygen.
Hydrogen.
Oh.
It's made....
almost entirely...
of water.
All right.
Sorry if I overreacted in there.
Just, uh, realizing I was wrong
about the only
original idea I ever had.
Yeah. What else did you learn?
They give off infrared
light when they move.
- Mm-hm.
- Like, so much.
I don't know how they
store all that energy.
But, uh, their wavelength is
exactly the Petrova frequency.
The light is how they move.
Yeah, they consume the sun's energy,
and then they expel it for propulsion.
They toot to scoot basically.
Why did it go to Venus?
I don't know.
Okay. We'll tell you.
What?
I have 347 other biologists in 21
countries mobilizing as we speak.
So thank you for your
help. I'm glad you didn't die.
Let's pack this up.
Pack up!
That's it?
- That's it, Carl?
- Talk to her.
You're taking all the stuff?
At the school you said
there were thousands
of people more
qualified than you, so
- I was being modest.
- I don't need modest.
I need people who
think they're right
when everyone else
thinks they're wrong.
I need people who
piss other people off.
That's me!
Do you want to be on a project?
If you...
If you think I can help, then...
Just answer the question.
I wanna help the world.
I left you three dots.
Just three, huh?
Plus the one you killed.
I would take the three.
- Yes?
- I'll take the dots.
Get to work, Dr. Grace.
The world is counting on you.
Hey, Carl?
This is Carl.
Imagine for a second that you're
an interstellar microorganism.
I'm not doing that.
Why would you leave
the sun and go to Venus?
Why not stop at
Mercury? It's closer.
Maybe fresh air?
Venus's atmosphere
is mostly CO2.
Maybe that's fresh air to them.
You don't know what
these little space dots like.
Hey, Carl?
Do we have an expense account?
We don't.
But I do.
All right, I got
something for you.
Thank you.
- Do you have a coupon?
- We don't need a coupon.
- We're the government.
- Which government?
All of 'em.
- So this box is Venus.
- The box is Venus.
It's set to emit the same
infrared light frequency
as Venus's CO2 atmosphere.
So if the dots move
when you turn the lights on,
that means they're
looking for CO2.
Thus proving the
Carl Hypothesis.
Sick.
Sorry.
- All right.
You ready?
Uh-oh.
Why you saying "Uh-oh"?
The Astrophage
moved off the slide.
Huh?
We lost them.
What do you mean, we
lost them? Go get them.
If I open the door in the light,
they're gonna escape, and
then we'll lose them forever.
At least now they're in the box.
So we'll just
turn the lights off.
But there'll still be light.
It's gotta be total darkness.
Okay, so just put this
box in another box.
Nice.
Go ahead and close it. Over.
I can hear you.
Entering phase two.
I'm in.
Please report. Over.
There's one.
There's two!
Come on! Get the third one.
Got sample three.
The Three Musketeers.
The Three Stooges.
Uh-oh.
What? What?
Are you sitting down?
No, I'm standing
like a grown man.
'Cause there's a fourth.
What?
We're fathers, Carl.
Now I'm sitting down.
Stratt.
Carl and I made a baby.
What?
We figured out how
Astrophage breeds.
Don't move.
Wheels up.
You know, Carl, when Stratt
said she was sending a jet,
I thought you meant
like a
- PJ or something.
- I thought of it. I know.
Take this.
It's been a long time
since I've taken a pill
from a stranger without
knowing what it was.
Stop! Stop!
Dr. Grace, how was your flight?
- Where are we?
- The ocean.
The Astrophage reproduction.
Can you do it at scale?
Oh, in theory, you just get a
bunch of elbow-shaped pipe,
put sunlight in one end--
Excuse me for a second.
- Write it down.
- Yes, ma'am.
and IR light and CO2
in the other. Repeat.
- Anything else you need for--
- Just some water.
He gave me a pill and
it's still in my throat.
Two venti coffees.
Thank you so
much. Water for him.
Or coffee. That's
- I need both.
- Or not.
Okay, so this is
kind of a tough room,
so don't take it personally.
I don't need anything fancy.
As long as there's a bed
and a shower I'm good.
- I can't do this.
- Come on. Yes.
- I can't. I can't.
- You're doing great.
Everyone, this is Dr. Ryland
Grace from the United States.
Please go here. Thank you.
And he figured out how
to breed Astrophage.
How did you do it?
How long does the process take?
Does it reproduce
by mitosis or meiosis?
What is the incubation period?
Um
Carl and I made a mini
Venus out of a plywood box,
and as soon as the
samples recognized
the, uh, spectral signature
of CO2, they were....
They were like,
"Whoomp! There it is!"
Okay.
- You can sit down.
- Who's Carl?
While your experiment
was crude and clumsy,
our scientists have
replicated his results.
I'm sorry, how did
you see, how did you?
We estimate an eight-day doubling
time under optimal conditions.
- Dr. Grace is right.
- Oh.
It is the CO2.
That's why they're
going to Venus.
- Please say it for everyone.
- That's why they're going to Venus.
So that's why they're
going to Venus,
is what Dr. Grace wants to say.
They're going to breed.
Whoomp! There it is.
I really like him.
How long to make
two million kilogram?
Two million?
Two million is-- Why....
on earth would you need
that much Astrophage?
Nobody told him?
- He has no clearance.
- Please stand up, Dr. Grace.
Stand up.
I hereby grant you
top-secret clearance
to all information pertaining
to Project Hail Mary.
What's Project Hail Mary?
All right.
The sun is not
the only star dying.
There is a clear
pattern of infection.
Every star was infected
by its neighbor except one.
- Tau Ceti?
- Tau Ceti.
That's right. 11.9
light years away.
It is uninfected despite being well
within the cluster of infected stars.
- Why?
- Why? Tell him.
We don't know!
Which is why we
decided to build a ship
to go there and find out.
It's 11.9 light years away.
You can't just build
an interstellar ship.
Oh yeah, we can.
The ship is not
really the problem.
The energy required to
power the ship is the problem.
It was the problem.
The Astrophage is the fuel.
Provided we can
make enough of it.
And for that, we
need you, my friend.
Me?
Ooh. Those little guys
store a lot of energy.
One mistake and that much
Astrophage could vaporize California.
That's true, which is why
you now live on a boat
in the middle of the
ocean in case "boom".
- I live on a boat?
- You do.
So you wanna build a
near-light speed spaceship,
have it travel further than
any human-made object
has ever traveled, and visit
a star just to "see what's up"?
Yeah.
And then what?
There won't be enough
fuel for a round-trip
so they send their findings
back to Earth on probes.
And the astronauts...
- die in space?
- Yes.
Space.
Any other plans
you've thought of?
Anything else you're
kicking around?
There are infinite possibilities
for this to go wrong.
It almost certainly won't work.
It's what you Americans
would call a long shot.
Hail Mary.
I get it now.
The alternative is
to just do nothing...
and to starve and
to kill each other
and watch everything on this
planet go extinct, including us.
So...
That's a long time
to be in space.
They'll be in
comas for most of it.
But is that even safe?
Nothing about this is safe.
We only need three.
A pilot.
An engineer.
And a scientist.
Commander Yáo.
I must have known you,
but I just don't remember.
You make a funny face
in literally every picture.
You must have been very smart...
and strong
and brave.
Ilyukhina.
First, I owe you
three bags of vodka.
You seemed to have
had a lot of friends.
This picture of you, what looks
like sneaking into the Kremlin is...
legendary.
I wish you were still here.
I wish I wasn't alone.
I wish I was...
doing a better job, I just, uh
You were both very loved.
You deserve much more than this.
I'll do my best to make
sure that you don't...
you know, that you didn't--
I'll do my best.
Approaching Tau Ceti orbit.
Prepare for engine cutoff.
- Fourteen, thirteen ...
- What?
- Why engine cutoff?
- twelve...
- Seems like something
- eleven...
- we should talk about.
- ten...
Pilot detected.
What? No. I'm not a pilot!
- six, five...
Four, three...
- What happens at zero? I mean--
- two...
You are now orbiting Tau Ceti.
What the fudging fudger?
Petrovascope operational.
It's Tau Ceti.
You have a Petrova line.
But you're not dimming.
Why?
What is that?
Blip-A detected.
What's a Blip-A?
No, no. No, no, no.
Let's go. Let's go, Mary.
No-No-No-No!
Pilot detected!
Please engage restraint.
- Pilot detected.
- We're getting outta here.
Engage spin drive.
- Engage the spin drive.
- Incorrect.
Welcome to the Hail Mary.
Is it this thing?
Erratic maneuver detected.
Yeah.
Blip-A detected.
What do they want?
What?
Blip-B detected.
What's a Bl--?
Current distance from
Hail Mary is 800 meters.
It's sending me something.
It could be a message.
It could be a bomb.
Is it a bomb?
Shields up!
There are no shields
on board the Hail Mary.
Why not?
Thirty meters.
Twenty meters. Ten.
Well, I guess there's egg
on both our faces, huh, Mary?
Blip-C detected.
What's that?
Why is it moving so much
slower than the last one?
They think I'm dumb.
If we were gonna catch
it, what would we do?
Would you like to go on
a space walk, Dr. Grace?
To begin your space walk, put on
your EVA suit and proceed to the airlock.
Yeah.
Yes!
No.
That's just crazy.
Righty tighty, lefty loosey.
Xenon's a gas. I think
this thing's broken.
We need equipment to analyze
the Astrophage at Tau Ceti. Correct?
- Dr. Grace.
- Sorry. Hi.
Most of this equipment
won't work in zero gravity.
And we have a team to develop and build
zero gravity versions of this equipment.
We would need years for
that, and we have months.
What's the alternative?
We make gravity.
Centrifuge?
Centrifuge.
They used them to make butter
during the Civil War, actually.
It's a fun fact.
Lab operational.
Still Xenon!
Up is down! Left is
right! Xenon's a solid!
Aliens are real!
I'm wrong about everything
and everything's wrong.
Lefty tighty, righty loosey.
I mean--
Oh no!
Foreign presence detected.
You're a long way from home.
I'm a long way from home too.
Blip-D detected.
Is that me?
My ship.
I don't understand.
Oh.
You want me...
to go back in my ship?
But I just got here.
Okay.
I'll talk to you later.
Bye.
What are they doing, Mary?
It is not advised to modify the
centrifugal settings of the ship.
Thank you, Mary.
What?
Oh my.
This is new.
Anybody home?
I like what you've
done with the gravity.
I made you a ship.
It's ramen.
I only made one. I'm...
not sure how many
of you there are.
Hi.
No-No-No-No-No!
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
You scared me when you went:
Wow.
Can't seem to see a face.
Mysterious.
Faces are overrated.
You like tapping, huh?
This is fun.
You're pointing.
You're not tapping. Sorry.
Another present.
I don't have one of these.
I love it! Thank you.
What, I put this on my head?
Take off my head?
Take my helmet off?
No.
It'll...
That's a big ask.
Oh.
This has taken a turn.
Thank you for what I
hope is not handcuffs.
And I'm sorry about
the whole helmet thing.
Unfortunately, I need
oxygen to breathe, so....
Two rings of eight.
O2.
You little rascal.
This is oxygen!
I still don't think I can
do it, though. Sorry.
It's just, uh
if I'm wrong, I'm really wrong.
Okay.
It's the Petrova line.
We're here for the same reason.
You have a Petrova
line problem too.
You need to solve
it. I need to solve it.
That's why you made me this.
I'm gonna take that as a yes.
If we're gonna save our planets, we
have to learn how to communicate.
You know, they say math
is the universal language.
I thought maybe we
find out if that's true?
You see the numbers?
Oh, you want this?
Whoa! Christmas Eve, that is...
really hot in there.
Is that ammonia?
Anyway, that's
Look, see the numbers?
No. They're on the other side.
Do it again. If you
do it again and you--
Don't let it snap back.
Don't do it. Don't do it.
Hold it like that.
And you look--
Wow. Wow.
How 'bout something else?
Look at this.
A clock.
We both have time. Right?
These are the hands,
and these are the numbers.
One, two, three. They
point to the numbers.
And if you'll notice, there's numbers
there, and there's also numbers here.
Okay.
It is dark.
I got an idea.
Wait.
Don't Yeah.
Don't go anywhere. Stay.
Oh. Oh yeah.
I'm Grace.
I'm gonna call you Rocky.
You know, 'cause you
look like a giant rock. Oh!
Um, I'm fine.
Echolocation. Right?
You need surfaces to see.
Try this.
You see the numbers?
What is that?
Is that good?
Jazz hands means "good"?
We do this.
Your version of this...
is our thumbs up.
Nope. That's thumbs down.
We do the thumbs up.
It's close enough.
You want me to wait? I wait?
Yeah. No.
I'm really excited to be
working with you on this.
Fired up.
I'm sorry I'm talking so much.
It's just, I haven't been
around anyone in a long time.
Oh.
What the have we got here?
It's a clock.
I showed you a clock and....
and you're showing me a clock.
We're, uh, clock bros.
Right.
Um, I gotta be honest.
I'm not sure I'm
getting all of this.
Check this out.
I thought I might record you.
Oh, no-no. No. That's okay.
It's just a microphone.
Works like this.
Looks like they say,
uh, let's start with one.
One.
No-No, wait, wait, wait. Sorry.
Okay. One.
And
One!
Okay.
So, uh I met an alien.
And we're learning
to communicate.
Let's do names.
Okay, let's start with you.
Rocky.
You done?
My name-- Can't
wait to hear this.
is Grace.
What's your word for
my name? Go ahead.
You know, enough
to order at restaurants.
We have about 250 words.
My atmosphere would
kill him and his, me.
But I like to keep a wall up
in my relationships anyways.
He's a mechanic, I think.
He uses a metal form of xenon.
He can make anything.
Look at this.
I'm calling it "xenonite."
And if I can't understand
what he's saying,
which is most of the time,
he puts on a little puppet
show for me and my tiny brain.
And you know
what? I don't mind it.
He's kinda growing on me.
At least he's not
growing in me, you know?
Which was a concern
for a little while.
His sun is dying too.
So maybe we can help each other.
Recognize this?
We call it "Astrophage."
It means star-eater.
"Astrophage on me star.
Bad, bad, bad, bad,
bad, bad, bad." Yeah.
Same.
Why are you alone?
Twenty-three?
Wow. Um
What happened to them?
I'm sorry.
How did they die?
Oh.
Um
There were three of us, and...
two died on the way here.
I wish I knew why.
Now it's only me.
Correction.
Deal.
Called a fist bump, by the way.
What's that?
"Fist my bump"?
No. It's fist bump.
It's not the same.
Exactly. The Astrophage
has to reach Tau Ceti.
Otherwise, we wouldn't
see the Petrova line.
Do we really need
this whole model?
Right.
Oh boy.
You know, I used to have
one of these in my classroom,
and it was a lot
simpler to set up.
One sec. What? What?
That is a great question.
You know what? Try this.
Why is a schoolteacher
in space, question?
- No.
- Don't like that voice.
- Can't unhear it, really.
- Scary.
Let's try this.
- Ooh.
- Nope.
- Why is a schoolteacher in space?
- No need.
No need to even continue. Nope.
Why is a schoolteacher in space?
What's so funny, question?
- I mean...
- It has charm, but no.
Meryl Streep?
Why is a schoolteacher in space?
She can do anything.
Don't think so.
Why is a schoolteacher in space?
That's not bad.
- I like.
- All right.
And in answer to your question,...
I have no idea what
I'm doing in space.
I don't remember.
Is okay.
Grace find out when
Grace go home.
I'm gonna go to sleep.
No understand word.
Sleep?
Uh, just, you go like this.
Died? Is died? Died?
No-No-No-No-No.
No. Not died. Just lay here for
29,000 seconds and then we...
- wake up!
- Oh. Understand.
We call this:
Okay. Here we go.
Sleep.
Good night, sir.
I watch Grace sleep.
No, that's fine.
That's a little weird.
I'll be good.
- Good night!
- No, not safe.
Eridians must watch sleep.
That's really interesting.
That sounds like something
We can unpack that tomorrow.
Rocky watch crew many days.
Crew not wake up.
That's where you're gonna be?
No, it's usually closer.
On your chest.
I wonder if it would work
from a little farther back.
But Grace won't feel
comfortable and safe.
Well Hey, look, I'm seeing
so many sides of you
lately, and it's great.
Right now I'm seeing
the underside of you.
Kind of a side sleeper
anyway. Good night.
So, we watch each other sleep.
Eridians don't sleep
like a human does.
They seem
legitimately paralyzed.
If danger comes,
he can't wake up.
It's a survival norm.
Someone has to keep you safe.
Attention: Mission update.
Scientific objective completed.
Flight team, I want you
to meet Dr. Ryland Grace.
He is currently the world's leading
authority in Astrophage biology.
Dr. Grace, these are the three
astronauts going on the mission
and their backups
for redundancy.
Yáo, Ilyukhina, and DuBois.
Our pilot, engineer,
and science officer.
It's an honor.
I'm excited to share what I've learned
about Astrophage and spin drives.
We have 1,009 of these Little Engines
That Could on the Hail Mary and--
Okay.
- You're doing great.
- What?
Once the mission is complete,
we have the option to
end our lives on our terms.
The alternative is slow
miserable death by starvation.
I want to do lethal injection
with a little bit of heroin.
I will have what she's having.
Following on from
Dr. Grace's discovery,
we've built an IR emitter
set to the wavelength of CO2,
which attracts the Astrophage
to this revolver face.
The drive then rotates
outwards, yeah?
We increase the IR, the
Astrophage get excited,
thrust the ship forward,
and so on and so on.
This is less than a
gram of Astrophage,
and we only need
a fraction of this
for this demonstration,
if you want to take a look.
To do what?
To melt a metric ton of metal.
Powerful stuff.
Commander Yáo, I really
appreciate what you all are doing.
You would do the same.
I would choose
just not to go at all.
I don't have the bravery gene
that you all have. Trust me.
It's not a gene.
You just need to find
someone to be brave for.
Movement detected.
Hi, Grace.
You're in a ball!
So Rocky no die in
Grace atmosphere.
- I come up.
- Oh, you're coming up.
Foreign body detected.
Grace and Rocky big science
how to kill Astrophage together.
I keep going this way?
- This room boring.
- Rocky!
Science. Save Earth.
Save Erid. Good plan.
- No! No! No!
- What this down here, question?
Amaze, amaze, amaze.
Rocky want to see
human technology.
Dirty, dirty,
dirty. Dirty, dirty.
- Why room so messy, question?
- Well, I wasn't expecting
- company, was I?
- Is this room
- for garbage?
- Oh.
- Dirty, dirty, dirty.
- No. This is the lab.
This is where the
science happens.
- What this? What this?
- That's the evaporator. Whoa!
What this?
That is the disco ball.
That makes me happy.
Rocky will build workshop here.
Will need much room for Rocky
and much less space for Grace.
What is happening here?
We go Petrova line.
We collect Astrophage.
We study it. We go home.
We collect. We save Earth.
And when you say
"we," uh, where?
I see Grace!
- Apology, apology, apology.
- Whoa! Enough!
- Rocky, stay!
- Rocky new to ball.
Rocky, my hand is up.
We can't just show up in
a space ball unannounced
and move into someone
else's spaceship. Right?
- There has to be boundaries.
- Boundaries.
- We have one mission.
- Mission.
But we're two
distinct individuals.
- Individuals.
- Both
working on our distinct
individual parts of that mission.
Mission.
- Separately.
Okay.
- Where my bedroom?
- Bedroom?
For what?
So I have a new roommate now.
Be careful back there, okay?
The chore wheel's
pretty lopsided.
Where on earth does that go?
- Not on Earth. More high.
- It goes this way?
- Wall. Wall.
- All the way out to here?
- Yes. Out, pointy.
- What?
He tells me what to do,
he tells me why to do it,
he tells me how to do it,
he tells me when to do it.
And then when I do it, he's
like, "What are you doing?"
I'm just saying you're
gonna get out of the ball
to get into a much bigger ball?
Yes. For sleeping.
- Sounds like you're having an argument.
- You don't even use a bed!
- Conflict is normal amongst crew members.
- You have the Hellraiser thing that
you sleep on.
- What do you need a bed for?
- Grumpy, angry, stupid.
How long since
last sleep, question?
Don't talk to-- Armando.
Yes. Can I help you?
You're doing this.
It's a lot of this.
And then he's like, "No
understand, no understand."
And then it's like
"Need a word."
You know what
the word is? Bossy.
I'm like one of the villains
in the Superman movie.
I'm just, like, trapped in hell.
Get me out of here!
His eating habits are...
exotic.
Grace look disgust when eat.
How do you look when you eat?
- Is look beautiful.
- Show me.
Oh my God.
He has incredible hearing.
He can see through walls.
Personal space is at a premium.
Who is Grace
talking to, question?
There's no way you
can hear me right now.
Can hear. Who
are you talking to?
You can hear this?
Yes. Grace say,
"You can hear this?"
- What about this?
- Yes.
Oh my God. Look at this.
Look how far away he is.
- That is where he is.
- Hello, Grace.
- He's right here. Okay?
- Hello, Grace Friend.
Did Grace find
sampler instruction?
Yes, I found the
sampler instruct--
sampler instructions.
He's really smart
about some things.
Oh my God, he's got a gun!
Oh. This? No, no, no.
This to screen in front,
and now this to that over here.
Now Rocky can hear screen.
-Please don't point it at me.
-Oh. Point over here.
- Yes.
- Oh, okay. Now over there.
You're pointing at me again.
But his species doesn't
know about things
like relativity and radiation.
And the rest of the crew?
- In mid of ship. There.
- In here?
And where did you
keep the Astrophage?
Fuel tanks next to
Rocky workshop there.
I think the radiation is what
made your crew sick, Rock.
The Astrophage probably
just protected you from it.
This isn't something
that you could have fixed.
But I guess together we're,
you know, pretty smart.
Since we're only gonna
be able to intersect
with the Petrova line
for a few seconds,
we're not gonna have enough
time to get a good sample.
Too fast. Do puppet
show. Too fast.
I don't want to do
the puppet show.
No, do puppet show.
This is us. We're,
you know, flying along.
The problem is, because the
solar system is constantly moving,
the Petrova line is gonna
constantly be moving. Right?
Am I still doing it?
- You still want it?
- Yes, yes. Show time.
So we're not gonna have
time to get the sample.
No, no, no. Use planet
gravity to move with line.
You mean sort of
like rest in its orbit?
Yes.
- I didn't think of that.
- I did.
We figured out a plan.
We're gonna orbit the planet
where Astrophage breeds,
collect a sample and figure
out why it's not eating Tau Ceti.
Who is Grace talking to?
I'm not talking to anyone.
I need a break.
- Break from what?
- Oh my God.
Forget it, this
isn't gonna work.
150 million kilometers away.
Racing along at 162
kilometers per second.
Means we should
arrive at Tau Ceti-e at--
Arrival at Tau Ceti-e in 11
days, 3 hours and 14 minutes.
- Thank you, Mary.
- You're welcome, Dr. Grace.
- You're welcome, Rocky.
- Welcome to Earth.
- You are in the Mental Health Node.
Whoa, whoa, whoa!
Careful, Rocky.
Rock. Look out below.
The beach is always changing.
You could go to the
same spot every day,
you're always looking
at a different beach.
Trees.
And you climb, and you
climb to the top if you can.
He's so excited about us
both getting to go home.
There's no harm in
pretending for a little while.
- Touch the wave, Rock.
- Touching the wave.
Is wiping out. Hanging ten.
Hey! Oh!
The Big Apple, baby.
In Three, Apollo trains him.
And in Seven, he
trains Apollo's kid.
- Yeah! Yeah! Yeah!
- Punch, punch, punch, punch.
-Nice!
- Adrian!
- Rocky!
♪ I say either, you say ♪
- ♪ Say either ♪
- Nope.
- ♪ I say neither, you say ♪
- ♪ Ne-i-ther ♪
No.
I like Earth.
I miss the fog.
What about you, Rock? What
do you miss most about home?
Hmm, my mate.
Wait, what?
- You got a mate?
- Yes.
I mean, not that you...
I mean, I'm sure... I'm
What's their name?
Name is:
It's beautiful.
Grace have mate, question?
No.
I mean, I did.
But she thought I had
my head in the clouds
and I didn't really want
to live in the real world.
She was right.
Anyway, now she's with Mark.
Rocky hate Mark.
But enough about
me. You have a mate.
How long you been together?
186.3 years.
It's like the honeymoon phase.
- No understand.
- That's a joke, Rock.
That's a long time. You've
been together a long time.
Is not enough.
♪ Like brothers ♪
♪ The future's in the air ♪
♪ I can feel it everywhere ♪
♪ Blowing with the
wind of change ♪
Permission to come
aboard, captain.
You're already aboard.
Did you get your free hat?
- Yeah, I kinda bought them.
- Oh.
- You don't sing, huh?
- Yeah, I do.
I actually sang in an
Eastern German youth choir.
You're very mysterious.
No, I'm not.
I always wanted to be....
mysterious.
Talk too much.
That's my problem.
Like right now.
I didn't mean to bother you.
You don't bother me.
It is such a weird party.
Is it?
Yáo is singing.
Everyone's so happy.
People are...
hooking up, and they all
know they're gonna die.
Camaraderie helps them
do their job, you know.
Not so much me. So...
Must be hard having
to ask everybody to...
you know.
Actually it isn't.
Yeah.
So, what do you think?
You think you're
gonna pull it off?
What, the whole thing?
Yeah.
God willing.
You believe in God?
It beats the alternative.
♪ Just stop your crying ♪
♪ It's a sign of the times ♪
♪ Welcome to the final show ♪
♪ I hope you're wearing
your best clothes ♪
♪ You can't bribe the door
on your way to the sky ♪
♪ You look pretty
good down here ♪
♪ But you ain't really good Oh ♪
♪ We never learn
we've been here before ♪
♪ Why are we always
stuck and running from ♪
♪ The bullets? ♪
♪ The bullets ♪
♪ Just stop your crying
it's a sign of the times ♪
♪ We gotta get away from here ♪
♪ Just stop your crying
it'll be all right ♪
♪ They told me
That the end is near ♪
♪ We gotta get
away from here, oh ♪
♪ Just stop your crying
have the time of your life ♪
♪ Breaking through
the atmosphere ♪
♪ And it all looks
good from here ♪
♪ Remember everything
will be all right ♪
♪ We can meet again somewhere ♪
♪ Somewhere far away from here ♪
And that is enough.
I wish you could see this, Rock.
Rocky can see.
Boring.
What? This is not boring.
Name of planet Tau Ceti-e
is same name as star plus "E."
Boring.
I guess it could be a
little more evocative.
Astrophage sampler
in position, question?
Yep.
Trays are live,
looking both ways.
It is time go.
It's time go.
What is Grace doing, question?
I'm having a moment.
You know, back on Earth,
if you discover something,
you get to name it.
You were technically
the first one here, so
Yes, name is Medium-Rough
Texture Circle Planet.
'Kay.
Well, if Medium-Rough
Texture Circle Planet was taken,
we'll just have a backup.
Maybe go with
something personal.
Personal.
What's your mate's name again?
Name is
It's okay, it's
okay. I remember.
Need human word for Rocky mate.
Adrian.
Is beautiful.
- Well, that's weird.
- What?
It's the same amount,
both coming and going.
But if Astrophage
going to Adrian to breed,
there should be more leaving.
It should be double.
It doesn't make sense.
It's either not reproducing or it's not
leaving the planet for some reason.
Oh, my God.
What? What Grace see?
What Grace see, question?
Life.
This is not just Astrophage.
It's bacteria, it's protozoa.
- It's like cells on Erid.
- And Earth.
What this mean, question?
Well, if there's a
whole active biosphere
in the Petrova line, it stands to
reason there's a whole active biosphere
on Adrian, which means...
There's life on Adrian.
- Oh, Grace! Grace!
- Yeah?
Life. Life is reason.
Life is reason!
Yeah. You said it,
buddy.
- Life is the reason.
- No understand. No understand.
Use your words. Life's
the reason for what?
- Life is reason.
- Life is the reason for what?
Life is reason. Life is reason.
- Life is reason what?
- Life on Adrian is reason
Astrophage in balance.
Life on Adrian makes
Astrophage die.
- Like a predator.
- Yes.
That would keep
the population stable.
Grace, if we bring predator
home our stars not die.
Life is reason star not die.
Why didn't you just say that?
If there is some kind of
microbial predator on Adrian,
it'll be in the clouds
where Astrophage breeds.
Check. Oh.
The problem is this ship wasn't
built to go into the atmosphere.
If we get within five kilometers,
we'll be ripped into a million pieces
and then we'll burn up.
Game over.
Game not over. I make
chain. I make long chain.
I put collection device on end.
Oh, yeah, yeah. Five
kilometers of chain. Sure.
- Guard me!
- Like this chain. Look.
- You can do that?
- Yes.
Kinda like fishing.
What that?
Oh, oh!
Fishing! Can you believe it?
- It could work.
- Thumbs up, baby.
Hello, Earth!
Plan is like fishing.
We get very close
to Adrian atmosphere
and lower collector
into clouds with chain.
Then Grace go
on hull to reel it in.
If ship not at precise
angle and speed, we die!
Example!
We must fly backwards
to keep proper velocity,
even though Grace still
have no pilot experience.
But I've been
practicing, haven't I?
- More! No. Left. Be left.
- What?
More left. More left.
Is perfect. No. Wrong.
- Erratic maneuver detected.
- No. Wrong way. Wrong angle.
Bad, bad, bad. Good, good, good.
Good. Bad. Not enough.
Not enough. Too much, too much, too much !
- Left, left, left.
- I'm barely pulling it!
No, is bad. Grace Rocky dead.
- All Rocky plural, all Earth, die.
- Power off.
We die. We die. We die.
Rocky has built
predator collector.
Rocky chain spooled and ready.
Grace pilot
training not as good.
What think, Earth?
Hello?
- They can't hear you, pal.
- What?
We're not actually talking
to Earth. Earth's too far away.
We just record these messages
and we tell 'em what we've learned,
and then when we're done,
we'll send them all back in a probe.
Why not you tell them yourself
when you return home, question?
Yeah.
This is a one-way
ticket for me, pal.
What?
We had enough
Astrophage to get here
but not enough to get back.
So, what happens
Grace, question?
Oh I got enough food to last me
at least a couple years.
Maybe a couple
more if I stretch it out.
So Grace die, question?
Yeah, once we're done, I'm...
I'm gonna die.
Why didn't you tell me?
It slipped my mind.
No. Grace say Grace go home.
Look.
- Listen. Listen. Listen.
- No. No.
I got to meet you.
I got to do all
this amazing stuff.
I'm good. I've
made peace with it.
What mean? What
mean "make peace"?
It means...
I know I'm not going home...
I know why...
and it's okay.
- Thumbs up?
- No.
- Tiny thumbs up?
We got stars to save. Okay?
- Grace?
- Yeah.
You are
Need word.
W-W-What word do you need?
To risk self to help another.
Uh, dumb.
Grace?
How much Astrophage
you need, question?
Two million kilograms.
I can give.
I go home six years slower.
That's too much.
Rocky watch crew die.
Could not fix.
Grace say Grace will die.
Rocky fix.
Grace go home.
Okay.
I thought you made
peace, question?
I didn't mean any of that.
That's just something you say.
Thank you.
Get over here.
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
What? What's happening?
- A hug.
- Oh! Hmm.
It's usually not something
one does by themselves.
Oh. Wait, I do the same?
Would you just get in here?
How do you know
when the hug is done?
- You just feel it.
- Oh.
Are you feeling it now?
Nope.
Oh. Oh, okay. Yeah.
We ran the sampler
simulation again this morning.
Shapiro and DuBois
nailed it again.
Okay. What about the others?
They'll be ready.
I expect so.
They have a great teacher.
Can you take a
compliment please?
No.
It's an order. Okay?
Okay. If it's an order,
I'll take it. Thank you.
Good.
What do you think?
It's pretty impressive.
- Yeah.
- You're
You're good.
Three days, huh?
Yeah.
So, what are you gonna
do for the next 20 years?
You got a plan?
Manual mode activated.
Go.
That's not half bad!
Is full good.
Time go fishing, question?
It's now or never.
- Three thousand meters.
- Three thousand.
Probe signal good.
Now comes the fun part.
Grace go out on hull
to retrieve collector?
- No fun at all.
- It's a joke.
Oh, humor. Confusing.
You gotta be kidding me.
What problem, question?
It's fine. It's just
the sky is slightly on fire.
Words of encouragement.
You can't just say
"words of encouragement."
Words of great encouragement.
Nope.
- Did you feel that?
- Yes.
I'm not worried.
Are you worried?
Yes.
Great.
Collector is closed.
Move winch into position.
Whoa!
How long is this
supposed to take?
Collector should be here soon.
Yeah. It's here.
Amaze, amaze, amaze!
Careful. Collector important.
Yup.
Altitude warning.
Oh, hurry, hurry.
Hurry, hurry.
Grace?
Grace, status update.
Status update.
Grace?
Grace is safe, question?
I'm okay.
Good, good, good.
Come inside with
predator collector now.
Uh
Why not moving, question?
Warning! Exterior
temperature elevated.
Must move now. Go, go.
No, Grace. Bad
idea. Come inside.
I'll be there in a minute.
No, no, no, no,
no. Grace will die.
Can repeat mission.
Can try again later.
I don't think there
is gonna be a later.
Abort, abort, abort.
Grace will die.
No-No-No-No-No-No-No-No-No.
- Grace?
- I'm here!
Amaze, amaze, amaze!
Grace okay, question?
Well, I'm not dead, so yes.
Good, good, good, good.
Where is that noise coming from?
Noise is from all around.
It's loudest at port
side of bedroom.
The gravity's
tearing the ship apart.
We leave now, question?
We leave now, statement.
Hull pressure warning.
Hull bending in big
room below bedroom.
That's the fuel tanks.
- Oh. Bad, bad, bad.
- Well, it's not great.
- Bad, bad, bad.
- Warning.
Everybody, calm down. Calm down!
Try and keep yourself
together, Mary.
- Stop engine now?
- Not yet.
We need to get into
orbit or we'll crash!
I have an idea. First, no crash.
Then, not explode. Deal?
Deal!
Hold on.
Now?
Wait.
Now? Now?
Now!
Did we do it?
Why ship moving, question?
There's a hole in it!
Hull breach.
Port side fuel
compartments 11 and 12.
Grace. What happening, question?
The fuel is migrating to Adrian!
Eject bad fuel bay, question?
Yeah.
Jettison port fuel tank
compartment 12. Confirm.
Rocky!
Jettison port fuel tank
compartment 11. Confirm.
Eject other fuel bay.
One nanogram of Astrophage just
isn't enough to blow up a building.
The quartermaster gave him
one milligram by mistake.
That's a million
times the heat energy
that they're prepared for.
A measuring mistake killed
my entire science team?
It doesn't matter.
We have to launch.
If we miss the orbital window,
it'll set us back months.
Yeah, but if no one's trained to
do the mission, it won't matter.
Casualty projections go
up exponentially if we delay.
We launch on schedule with
a replacement science officer.
Okay, but
who?
I mean, that...
I'm not an astronaut.
I don't need an astronaut.
I need an expert on
Astrophage who's mission-ready.
I'm not ready.
I don't have any training.
You'll pick it up.
I'm not an astronaut!
I put the "not" in astronaut.
I've never done anything--
I've never done a space
wa-- I can't even moonwalk!
I haven't done the
whole pool thing.
No, no, no. This is just
we do for the picture,
for social media.
I'm not heroic in any way.
I get sick on an elevator.
Oh, perfect. There's
no elevator on the ship.
I cannot do this.
You're smart.
You'll figure it out.
This might be very hard
for you to understand,
but some people are failures.
Some people don't
rise to the challenge.
You've been present
for every major scientific
or strategic meeting
we've had on the mission.
You're missing out an
important part of the mission
which is the suicide part.
Grace, you'd be in
very cool company.
If you don't go, you die anyway.
Yeah, but I die
in 30 years with--
"With the rest of us."
You have no immediate family.
You don't even have a dog.
So, just so I'm clear
you're asking me right now to...
give up my life.
I am. We all are.
- Can I think about this?
- You have three hours.
Eye movement detected.
Good morning, Dr. Grace.
I'll watch you sleep, pal.
But, uh
you gotta wake up.
I'm not sure what to do.
Done everything I can think of.
I made him a heat lamp.
And he left me one last message.
We have our predator.
Right now I'm
calling it "Taumoeba."
And I'm sure that
when you wake up,
you'll have a lot to say
about why that's a bad name
because it's just an
amoeba from Tau Ceti,
and we're putting "Tau"
in front of "amoeba."
But I would argue
there's an elegance to that.
A simplicity.
Let's not fight about it now.
Lets just-- We'll table it and we'll--
I did a test at different
atmospheric variables
and, fun fact, every
time I introduced nitrogen
it died.
And I know what you're thinking,
"Well, that's terrible
because that's a problem
'cause we need it to survive
in the conditions of Venus."
Obviously, I had to
figure out how to breed
a new strain of
nitrogen-resistant Taumoeba.
And guess what I used?
The breeder tanks that
we made with your xenonite.
And you know what?
Now we're just a
couple of very cool dudes
with their very own strain of
nitrogen-resistant Taumoeba.
Really, all we have to do now is
breed enough to survive the trip.
And you gotta wake up
because I don't know how to get
your half of the Taumoeba to Erid.
So
No pressure
but we did make a deal.
Shh.
Grace?
Rock, could you just give me a
little chance please to sleep a little?
Did we find predator?
No? Is yes.
Amaze, amaze, amaze.
Rocky breeder tank design.
Good job, Rock.
We can go home, statement.
We can go home.
Fist my bump.
Nope.
It's still not right.
- I'll do it.
- Good, good, good.
So what we do now, question?
We party.
Wow.
Is special clothing
for celebration.
You're making me think that
I have to, uh, up my game.
- What is this?
- If you don't mind.
- Rocky get one!
- There you go.
- Is good.
- Yeah.
It's not much. Just
a little something.
Your very own laptop.
My portable Earth
thinking-machine!
With all human knowledge.
- Thank, thank, thank.
- And just one more thing.
Yes?
What this?
It's Earth.
So you can remember me.
Rocky can't forget.
I didn't get you anything.
You gave me everything.
But if I were to
give you something?
It'd be pretty cool
to see your ship.
I understand that you think I'm
the right person for this mission.
But
I can't do it.
You'll find a solution.
You are my solution.
My place is in the classroom.
Stop pretending this
is about your students.
It's so insulting.
Grace, we will lose...
a quarter of the
world's population
in the next 30 years.
And that assumes that
the nations of the world
work together to ration food.
Which they won't.
So I'd double the estimate.
And if you would truly
care about the children,
or anyone else for that
matter, you'd get on that ship.
I understand the stakes.
I do.
But I don't have it in me.
My mind is made up.
I'm sorry, but, uh
you just can't
talk me into it.
I'm sorry.
I'm not trying to talk
you into anything.
I am...
trying to make you understand
what I'm about to do next.
Yeah? Please.
Stay calm. Come in.
What is this?
Mission plan will state that we induced
your coma early to maximize your safety.
You will be
remembered as a hero.
Come on.
- This is crazy.
- I have to do it.
You're not
Come on. What are you doing?
This may seem like
me betraying you,
but it's actually
me believing in you.
Sure feels like
you're betraying me.
- Don't make this harder, please.
- Come on, guys.
Let's keep talking about it.
Sit down and we
do it differently.
Yeah, he's running.
No.
No. No.
Carl. I can't do it.
No!
Don't do it! Don't
do it! Don't do it.
You know who you are.
Carl!
You're gonna do great.
I'm trying to think if
there's anything I forgot.
Fuel tank fix okay, question?
Oh, yeah, yeah.
They're working great.
Oh, good. Happy, happy, happy.
Well
My friend.
Yes, friend?
I'm not sure what
to say, so just gonna....
Grace?
No one to watch you sleep.
Yeah.
You are very brave.
Oh, I don't know about that.
You are bravest
human I have ever met.
Hey.
- Is joke.
- I know.
I only meet one
human, and is you!
I get it.
It's a good joke.
Good joke.
All right. Well...
Goodbye.
No understand word.
Means, uh, see you later.
But I won't see you later.
I know.
How do you say
goodbye back home?
We don't.
Hmm.
We do this.
Journey to Earth will take 4
years, 2 months and 11 days.
Lava! Lava!
Lava!
Contaminant detected.
There's a leak.
The problem is the xenonite.
The Taumoeba can get through it.
Probably 'cause we bred it
in the xenonite breeder tanks,
it evolved to escape it.
I was able to stop it before it
ate all the Astrophage on the ship.
Rocky's ship is
built of xenonite.
The Taumoeba will
already be in his fuel lines.
And he won't be able to find the
leak because the leak is the ship itself.
He'll be without
any fuel. Stranded.
His life support
systems will fail.
And if that doesn't kill him,
the radiation sickness will.
He's looking at a long
slow
painful death
alone.
I can't do both.
I can go home
or I can save Rocky.
I've sent you detailed
logs of all of our findings.
And enough Taumoeba
for you to start
your very own Taumoeba farm.
At least I never have to
hear you say, "I told you so."
Even though you were right.
I'm here, buddy.
Earth, Rocky.
Rocky, Earth.
Hello, Earth. I am Rocky.
I am Rocky from Erid.
I am not Rocky from
movie. No, no, no, no.
I'm pretty sure they know that.
I've left you detailed
logs of all of our findings
and I threw in a little
something else just for fun.
Hopefully it all makes sense.
And if not
You're smart.
You'll figure it out.
This is Dr. Captain Ryland Grace
reporting from the Hail Mary.
As the Eridians say...
Let's begin.
Good morning, Armando.
You shouldn't have.
That's a noogie.
I'm coming!
Why you always
gotta be so early?
Yeah. I know, and I ignored you.
Yeah. Okay.
Why? I thought this
was a safe neighborhood.
Okay. It's just, Armando
likes the fresh air.
Can we talk about the
water temperature a little bit?
It's amazing.
Just that you've done it at all.
Very cold.
And, before, it was boiling.
Is there an in between?
Please tell the biodome
illumination team that it's perfect now.
Oh, no, this is...
You know I'm a
sucker for the fog.
Yeah, pal.
Can I think about it?
Good morning, class.
Okay. Everyone take their seats.
Let's wake up.
Who can tell me
the speed of light?